A Finding Aid to the Terrain Gallery Records, circa 1950s-2005, bulk 1955-1985, in the Archives of American Art AAA.terrgall
Archives of American Art
- Exhibition Files, circa 1950s-2005; Series 4; 3.2 Linear feet Boxes 1-4, 6
  - Exhibitions (Box 1)
    - "Couples: Closeness and Clash in Art and Life" (1983 April 9-May 17), 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - "The Opposites This Summer" (1983 June 11-August) (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - "All Art Is for Life and Against U.S. Injustice to Central America" (1983 September 24-October 25), 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - "Chaim Koppelman, Pastels: Ideas/Objects/People" (1983 October 29-December 6), 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - "Big and Small: Small Paintings, Prints, Photographs, and Constructions by 40 Contemporary Artists" (1983 December 17-1984 January), 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - "Architecture: Matter and Space: An Aesthetic Realism Exhibition" (1984) (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - "Is Beauty the Making One of Opposites?" (1984 February 4-March 17) (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - "Continuity and Discontinuity" (1984 March 31-May 5) (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - "Animate and Inanimate" (1984 March 31-May 5) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - "Is Beauty the Making One of Opposites?, Intersection '85" (1985), 1984 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - "Nancy Starrels, A Retrospective Black and White Photographs" (1985 October-December), 1968; 1983-1985 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - "Terrain Gallery, 45th Anniversary Exhibitions" (2000 April 29-August) (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Lists (Box 4)
      - Terrain Gallery Exhibitions, 1955; 2005 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Printmakers Represented by Terrain Gallery, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Mailing Lists, undated 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 9-11)
  - Guestbooks, 1955-1983 (Box 4, Folder 12-19)
  - Printed Material (Box 4)
    - Press Clippings, 1967-2000 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Exhibition Announcements, circa 1955-1983 (Box 4, Folder 21)
      Oversized material housed in Box 6
    - Exhibition Catalog, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Miscellaneous Printed Material, circa 1964-1970s (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Oversized Printed Material - Exhibition Announcements, 1959-1983 (Box 6)
      Oversized material from Box 5, Folder 21
- Writings and Interview, 1955-1974; Series 5; 0.2 Linear feet Boxes 4-5
  This series contains annotated writings and an interview. Included are typescripts and handwritten drafts of writings by Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman, Regina Dienes, and others that were prepared for lectures held at the Terrain. Interspersed among the materials are exhibition announcements and clippings. Included are Chaim Koppelman's typescripts on printmaking and Dorothy Koppelman's essay-length pieces on the place of Aesthetic Realism in art history.
  There are annotated versions of an interview with Chaim and Dorothy Koppleman for the Village Voice conducted by David Bourdon to commemorate the Terrain Gallery's Eleventh Anniversary. The Koppelmans' discuss Aesthetic Realism and the influence of Eli Siegel's Theory of Opposites in their selection of artwork for the gallery's exhibitions. They also comment on several artists who had exhibited at the Terrain.
  - Writings by Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman and Others, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 24-25)
  - Writings by Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman and Others - "Twelve Talks,", 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Comments on Eli Siegal's "Fifteen Questions" by Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Writings by Chaim Koppelman, 1968; 1964 (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
  - Writings by Dorothy Koppelman, 1956; 1974 (Box 5, Folder 5-7)
  - Interview with Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Financial and Legal Records, 1955-1984; Series 6; 0.8 Linear feet Box 5
  This series contains ledgers, a financial report, memoranda, letters, invoices, lists of sales and loans of artwork to galleries and museums, and annotated receipts for works sold. Ledgers record the gallery's income, expenditures, cash disbursements, and sales of artwork; interspersed among the pages are notes, receipts, and miscellaneous tax information.
  Scattered legal documents include a certificate of incorporation for the Terrain Gallery with the Aesthetic Realism Foundation, a lease, and rider to the lease at the gallery's space at 39 Grove Street in New York. The files include correspondence, receipts, and a typescript of the gallery's statement of purpose, that was incorporated in the lease.
  The series is arranged as 2 subseries:
  6.1: Financial Records, 1955-1984
  6.2: Legal Records, 1964-1973
  - Financial Records, 1955-1983; 6.1
    - Ledgers, 1955-1984 (Box 5, Folder 9-15)
    - Loose Ledger Pages - Expenses and Disbursements, 1964-1971 (Box 5, Folder 16-18)
    - Financial Report on the Terrain Gallery, 1955-1983 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Sales and Loans to Galleries and Museums, 1973-1975; undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Consignment Receipts, 1964-1980; undated (Box 5, Folder 21-22)
    - Works on Consignment - Returned to Artist, 1960s-1975 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Receipts for Works Sold, 1955-1982 (Box 5, Folder 24-27)
    - Miscellaneous Letters, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Legal Records, 1964-1973; 6.2
    - Certificate of Incorporation, Aesthetic Realism Foundation, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Lease and Related Documentation - The Terrain Gallery, 39 Grove Street, New York, 1964-1969 (Box 5, Folder 30)
- Scrapbooks, 1955-2000; Series 7; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 5, 6
  This series houses 5 scrapbooks of exhibition materials. Two scrapbooks document the gallery's exhibitions from 1955-1960; three scrapbooks are devoted to individual exhibitions. Scrapbooks include scattered letters, statements to the press, gallery resolutions, schedule of events, lists of artists, price lists, mailing lists, consignment and invitational receipts. Among the printed material are annotated press releases, a catalog and clippings of exhibition reviews. Also found is a typescript of Eli Siegel's draft on Jackson Pollock.
  Four scrapbooks were dismantled but retain their original order.
  - Scrapbook 1: Terrain Gallery, 1955-1959 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Scrapbook 2: Terrain Gallery (Dismantled), 1955-1973 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Scrapbook 3: "Show-Down" (Dismantled), 1962 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Scrapbook 4: "Is Beauty the Making One of Opposites - Photography" (Dismantled), 1980 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Scrapbook 5: "3 Photographers at the Terrain Gallery" (Dismantled), 1999-2000 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Oversized Scrapbook 1 -Terrain Gallery, 1955-1973 (Box 6)
    Oversized material from Box 5, Folder 31.
- Photographs, 1957-circa 1980s; Series 8; 0.1 Linear feet Box 5
  This series contains black and white photographs of Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman and Harold Jacobs preparing for an exhibition; included is a snapshot of Chaim Koppelman with Vincent Longo and Gerson Leiber. There are some photographs of artwork.
  Two photograph albums contain black and white snapshots of Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman, Louis Dienes, Ad Reinhardt, Nancy Starrels and colleagues at exhibition openings.
  - Photographs of Chaim and Dorothy Koppelman and Others, 1957-1958 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1980s (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Album, "Personal and Impersonal" - Exhibition Opening, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Album, Terrain Gallery at the Audubon Opening and at Madison Square Garden, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 39)